You are about to learn one of the most intriguing of any indicator you're going to ever see
on the commodity market or for that matter for the stock market.
This is an indicator that I developed in 1998.
It's called Will Val, Will obviously my last name, Williams Val, it's about valuation.
In other words, what I was able to arrive at is a way that we can determine if a commodity
is overvalued or undervalued.
Now I'm not talking overbought or oversold here, that's a totally different concept.
What we're talking about is a valuation measure for virtually every single commodity that exists.
I'll be showing that to you in a moment, but what's really behind this is gold makes the
world go round.
And what I've noticed in my studies is that there is a ratio or a relationship between
the price of gold and all natural resources, well actually all markets move relative to
the price of gold.
When I was a young kid, I remember my grandfather saying that you could buy a man's suit for
one ounce of gold.
That was true then and it's true today.
Even with gold trading now at about $600 an ounce, you can buy a nice suit for that.
So did the price of suits go up or does the whole world revolve around gold?
That in fact what happened, it's the same ratio now between gold and wheat, between gold and
a man's suit or whatever it is.
So what we're looking at is the ratio of these markets to gold.
Now there are two types of future markets you need to be aware of.
One is the natural resource market, that would be real commodities.
Wheat, corn, cocoa, cotton, coffee, soybeans.
Those are real things that come from nature.
Then we have the abstract or man-made commodities.
That would be like the Swiss franc, euro dollars, treasury bonds, stock indexes, things of that
nature.
Those are things that are simply a figment of man's imagination.
We're going to look at those against gold and also another way of evaluating these man-made
commodities.
Well first we'll be looking at the natural resource commodities which value so well versus
the price of gold.
Now what you're going to be looking at and seeing is the relationship between the spread,
between the market and the price of gold.
Real commodities, value to gold.
The starting point is the spread between gold and the commodity.
I'll show you the formula and then in a moment we're going to look at charts so you can see
how this actually works.
I'm going to take a two week moving average of the spread.
The spread is simply the difference between gold and say pork bellies on a weekly basis.
We'll continue to use all weekly data here.
And I'm going to compare the two week moving average of the spread versus the 22 week moving
average of the spread.
Then I look at this current reading versus the highest and lowest reading of the last
three years.
In other words, the spread, the two week moving average of the spread, way out or above the
22 week average of the spread.
If so, we're in an overvalued zone.
If it's way far below the 22 week moving average, then we are in an undervalued zone.
And we're going to do this as a percentage of where we are now versus the last three
years.
That's the same formula that we looked at when we looked at the commitment of trader
report.
So we're going to simply have a window of the last three years and then see is the spread
relationship, the difference between the two week and the 22 week moving average excessively
high.
Is it at the high end of the spread ratio or is it at the low end of the spread ratio?
Now it's time to look at charts and what you're going to be seeing here is time after
time when this ratio is very high.
We are in an overvalued condition and when it's low, we are in an undervalued condition.
Let me be the first one to point out though that simply because we're undervalued does
not mean that a market is going to rally right now today, nor if we're overvalued, it doesn't
mean we're going to decline right now today.
What it means is that we are in the area, that's the important point, the area of undervaluation
and overvaluation.
And then what we'll do is start to bring in some timing mechanisms once we get these set
up tools.
But you're going to learn one of the most fascinating and wonderful set up tools that you've just
ever going to learn.
It's a great tool.